i'm going to share with you 10 effects
built into final cut pro 10 that you can
start using in your videos today
to spice it up a little bit to level up
and you're going to want to stay tuned
for all 10 effects because you probably
haven't heard of all of these and they
are going to turn you
into a pro editor in no time you got to
just press record hey guys my name is
noel molt with think media now number
one is to use text pop-ups this is
really popular when it comes to
youtubers and it's pretty simple inside
of final cut pro 10.
let me show you exactly what i'm talking
about and then i will show you how
to do it now let's get right into this
video because we have a lot to talk
about
yeah cheesy jokes welcome to the youtube
channel
so as you saw here this text was popping
up now i'm going to delete this and
start from scratch to show you guys
exactly
how to do this first things first you
want to go into your text and i'm just
going to go ahead and use
a custom one right here i'm going to
drag this over i'm kind of going to
resize this so that you know it's as
long as
what i am saying because i'm going gonna
have them pop up right as i say the word
it's gonna pop up you have a lot to talk
about
and it's gonna end right about there so
now that that's all set i'm gonna go
ahead and put in my text now that i have
my text on the screen it's pretty simple
what i like to do first is actually get
in here and just cut them
up to the words now this doesn't have to
be perfect because it's actually really
easy to
retime these so that it pops up at
exactly when you want to
but what i like to do is just really
quickly go through and cut these up
into the different words okay that's not
perfect but you know somewhere around
here now you can see that i've cut up
the titles
what i'm going to do now is start over
here on number one
and i am going to go to crop and then
change this to trim
so if it's on crop you don't want that
you want to change this to
trim from here all you have to do is
take this right side
of the box and start to drag it over
trimming off
every single word except for your first
word now what we could do is go over
click this again
go to trim and go ahead and do the exact
same thing we just did leaving our
second word
and our first word uh visible now now we
could just do this for every single text
but to speed up your workflow a little
bit you could do a copy and paste
all you gotta do is select one that
you've already trimmed you're gonna hit
command
c go to your next one and then you're
gonna hit command
option v from there it's going to chop
off most of the words and you just have
to drag it to
your next word so i'm gonna go ahead and
do this with the rest of them and it
really doesn't take that long and you
get yourself a really cool effect
by the end of it obviously on your last
one here you want to leave all the words
visible and now we can go through we can
watch it
and see if we need to kind of retime any
of the words
so i can maybe move this second to last
word
latte talk about we have a lot to talk
about
now that's looking pretty good and it's
as easy as that just using the trim tool
you also could use the mask tool but i
found for stuff like this
using the trim tool has found to be
easier for me next up i'm going to show
you guys how to blur out a piece of the
image whether you want to
censor it or hide it you can definitely
do that inside of final cut pro x
i've done this before for clients where
they needed to actually blur
out a brand or something in the
background like an address
and so i've had to use this before but
i'll show you how to do that right now
so first off we have our clip right here
and for this case i'm just going to blur
out my coffee cup because it's moving
and i'll show you guys how to kind of
move that around as well so the first
step you actually want to do
is to copy and paste the clip that you
are going to blur
and put one on top of the other so i'm
going to go ahead and move this
right on top of there now we have two
different clips now the top one is going
to be our blur and we're going to use a
mask
to control what we want to blur so let's
start with our effects and actually
going to pick out a blur there's two
that i like to use
one is just kind of your classic out of
focus blur and
the second one is more of a pixelated
blur so i'll show you where both of
those are if you go over here to blur
you can see right here that if i throw
this on top everything is out of focus
it's a pretty nice blur this is kind of
something that you would see on tv
however i'd like to use the pixelate
blur because it's just kind of fun and
funny and so i like to use that
sometimes if we click on all
and we go to search for pixel we'll see
a pixelate right here and if we throw
that
on top you are going to see that it does
this whole pixelating effect and you can
really choose how much you want to do
that let's get the copy up here
and maybe we want to make it even more
blurry now that we have
done our blur what we want to do next is
pick our mask
so i'm going to search for mask make
sure you're dragging this on
the top layer of your video and from
here
you can start to draw a mask around
exactly
what you want to blur out and we'll just
go ahead and blur out this entire
coffee cup now from here it doesn't look
too good but you can start to mess
around so that it fits around
whatever it is that you're blowing out a
bit better and then we want to
use the feather tool this is going to
make it look a whole lot smoother
you can even drag this past 100 if you
would like and so you know this is
looking fine for me
as far as a blur goes i think it looks
great now you can see the issue here is
that the coffee cup kind of comes into
the blower and it also goes
out of the blur so what i'm going to
show you how to do is how to move
this blur effect over neat overnight
over top of a moving object so i'm going
to move it to the first frame that it
comes into
which is right here and i'm just going
to drag this entire masking tool with
the blur effect
over that mug so that's right there i'm
going to go ahead and start my keyframes
underneath your mask you want to open up
your transforms and then you're going to
click this keyframe button right here on
position
and i like to go about three or four
frames and move
the mask if i'm moving it really fast
maybe i would do less every frame or
every other frame
but for something like this you can
really get away with three four frames
so i'm gonna start here and i'm just
going to move forward three frames
now that i move forward three frames i'm
going to move my mask
back up move forward three frames again
continue to move my mask
and i'm gonna do this for the entire
clip
now that i'm done you can see that the
mask is actually starting on the clip
and i don't want it to start on the clip
so to go to my first keyframe i'm going
to hit this button
right here and then i'm going to go back
a few frames
and move this all the way out so as we
go forward now it's going to come up
with the mug
which is perfect so let's hit play and
see what this looks like
awesome so the blur is moving around
with the mug and it looks great and
blurred
and the nice thing about this is now
that we've done a mask that's moving
we can actually replace this effect with
anything so if we wanted to change this
to our other blur it's really easy as
just
dragging this on top of the clip and
deleting the pixelate button
now we want to move this back up top
right where the pixelate was and from
here you can mess with the amount of
blur
you can make it more blurry less blurry
and you're gonna see that the same
effect happens all the movement have
been
kept the same but now it's just a
different type of blur
next up i'm gonna show you guys a little
stop motion effect i use this on my
wife's channel where her name pops up
and i kind of made this stop-motion
effect
with her name and i did that all
manually inside of final cut pro 10
so i'm going to show you exactly how i
did that so right here i did a little
text that says hello everybody and i'm
going to show you kind of what this
effect looks like
just kind of bounces back and forth kind
of like a stop-motion vibe
so it's really easy to do this what i'm
going to do is actually delete all of
this but keep
one of my text so first of all you want
to start with what it could be a picture
it could be text it really could be
whatever
you want it to be to kind of do this
effect and so all of it is going to be
the same whether it's text a picture
graphic whatever so the trick here is to
make your text three frames
long and then we're gonna go from there
so let's start by doing that one two
three i'm gonna go ahead hit b which is
the blade tool i'm going to chop
that off now i have this text that is
three frames long
and what you want to do is hit command c
command
v and you're going to paste it this next
one what you want to do is go to your
transform tool
and you want to adjust it just a little
bit you don't want to do it a lot but
you just want to change it
slightly you're then going to copy and
paste that one
right after it and you're going to do
the same thing you're just going to
adjust the rotation a little bit
maybe even the positioning a little bit
command
c command v and do the same
thing again make sure that it's not too
crazy all over the place or it might be
a bit too much
but you guys will get the hang of this
and then once you have about six to ten
of these
you're just going to command copy all of
them and paste those over and over again
so i'll just do a couple more here
adjusting it just slightly so that they
look a little bit different giving that
stop
motion effect all right now that i have
done seven of them i'm gonna go ahead
and hit play
and see how it looks i think it looks
pretty good and once you're happy with
how it looks all you have to do is copy
and paste that over and over again to
make it as long
as you want so i hit command c to copy
i'll hit command
v and then command v again again again
as long as i want it to last
and once you have it as long as you want
you have a really cool stop motion
effect to your youtube videos next up
i'm going to show you guys how to add
overlays to make your shot a bit more
interesting so
when i first started using this i was
actually adding some muzzle flashes to
some guns for these little action films
that i was shooting with my friends
but really this works for anything if
you want to do light leaks or any sort
of glitches
stuff like that this works really well
it basically just takes the black
in a background image or a video and it
makes it transparent so when you overlay
that
onto your video it's going to be
transparent and the black will go away
and everything else is going to be on
top of your image so right here you can
see that the video is pretty bland
so i'm going to add some overlays just
to spice things up a little bit right
here i have this glitch overlay which i
think i just got off of youtube but it
kind of has these numbers kind of techy
uh computer things going on and so to
get rid of the black so that it shows
through
all you have to do is select the video
come up here to blend mode and you're
going to change that to
screen once you've done that you see
that you get these textures coming
through
and there is no more black screen
everything is transparent and it kind of
adds to this cool computer shot going on
so i'm gonna do the same exact thing
with this glitch effect right here which
we actually got off of story blocks
and so i'm gonna go to blend mode change
that again to screen and this is gonna
add a cool little transition to my next
shot and so let me show you what this
looks like now
i think it's really cool it adds a lot
to the shot and again you can get
creative with this and add tons of stuff
to your footage to make it look cooler
again those light leaks i've used a lot
of times different glitch effects stuff
like that
you can add on top of your video by
using the screen
blend mode i'm gonna show you guys how
to do this effect where it shows you the
before and after so if you're redoing a
room or if you're doing like a color
grade like i am doing here
you can actually do a sliding effect to
show the before
versus the after now right here i have
an adjustment layer and a clip and this
adjustment layer is just adding in my
color to my shot so you can see this is
what it looks like completely
flat and then you have your adjustment
layer now with this effect
you actually can't use an adjustment
layer and i'll show you why later so
what i want to do
is i want to copy this i'm going to
delete my adjustment layer and i'm just
going to paste that onto my
actual video now in order for this
effect to work
you do need two clips so i'm going to
copy
this exact clip and paste this now this
would work exactly if it was
your before shot and your after shot but
for me
i'm going to do before my color grade
and after my color grade so the top one
is going to be
the after shot and the before is going
to be the bottom so what i'm going to do
is delete everything on this bottom clip
to make it flat again
and you can see here if i mute this
video feed on top
our bottom layer is the before our top
layer is the
after from here you're going to go into
the transitions and you're going to go
to the search and look up
wipe and then you are going to drag the
wipe transition
onto the top layer you can actually
delete this end one and then you want to
extend this to make it a lot longer
and i'll show you guys what this looks
like now so right now
you can't even see the top layer you
just see the before shot which is down
here
and then as it plays through you are
going to see this wipe effect where it
shows you the color grade
that i've done you can adjust the
duration of the white by dragging it
left and right to make it longer or
shorter you can also
click on this transition and if you go
up here you're going to see that you
have a few different options so if you
want to go from left to right
you can also do that so now it is
dragging from
the left side to the right side you can
also change
the edge treatment i usually like to
leave this on feather where it just kind
of blends in
the two videos but you also could do
like a solid color like this
and make it white or black and you can
make the border color a lot
smaller and then that way it's kind of
showing you the before after
using a line of color to distinguish the
two now i don't know about you but have
you ever
accidentally gotten like a shotgun
microphone in your shot or a light in
your shot like you can see up here i
have this
light up there it was not supposed to be
in my shot but it was
but luckily in final cut pro there is a
fix that you can do for this
what you want to do is copy and paste
the clip that you are going to cover
and so we are going to cover up this
light right here so what i'm going to do
here is take this color right around
here because it's going to be
you know about the same color i'm just
going to drag that
over the light and then feather it out
so that no one can tell
in our effects we're going to be looking
for the mask tool and we can just draw a
simple mask i'm going to drag that on
top
now from here i just want to take this
color you know about the same
size of the light and then close that
off so
now that we've done that we are going to
take the feather option and put that to
a hundred
and then on our transform or you can go
to this right here
we are going to drag this up above now
if i completely remove
the bottom layer you're going to see
what's happening here i'm taking this
color
that i just got with the mask and then
i'm actually going to
feather this out a bit more so that it's
much smoother
and all you have to do is make sure that
it's completely covering
up that light or the microphone whatever
it is you want to hide in the shot
you can do this simply by adding in a
mask and dragging something over top of
it
and then by adding in some feathering
you're really going to smooth out this
shot so it looks nice and clean and now
it looks like there was no light ever
there so i can click this on and off you
can see that's before
and this is after another really cool
easy trick that i use for our think
media videos
is ken burns so you can see here that we
have a few different b-roll shots
and they're just pretty simple right
they're not too exciting they're pretty
boring there's not a lot of camera
movement happening
so what i'm going to do here is let me
trim this one first but what i'm going
to do here is add in some ken burns and
this is going to emulate a camera
movement so
all you got to do is click this arrow
right here we're going to go to crop
and down here you're going to hit ken
burns now here you have a start option
and the
n option so you can see it starts
completely wide and then it zooms in
ending a bit closer i'll show you what
this looks like
now it looks like there is a zoom
happening and so we're going to do the
same thing with this next shot but i'm
going to show you a few more things that
you can do with this
so here we can see that now it's doing a
zoom out where it's starting
in tight and then it is coming and
zooming out showing us the entire
shot but if you want to switch that
around so it's also zooming in
all you have to do is hit these little
arrows right here and that is going to
swap these for you so it's
also going to do another zoom in for you
and if we actually want to just switch
that back it's as simple as moving that
now if you want to make it
really drastic and zoom in a bunch you
can move these around as much as you
want i don't like to
make it super obvious i like to do kind
of a subtle
zoom in or zoom out effect but whatever
floats your boat you can definitely do
and mess around with these as well after
adding in those ken burns you can see
that this movement to the shot really
just adds a lot to these b-roll clips
and gives it a bit more spice and i
definitely think it's something worth
messing with because it can really take
your shot to the next level just adding
that little bit of camera movement
really can make a big difference for
this next effect we use this all the
time at think media this is when our
text
swooshes in and swooshes out and we add
in the sound effects i'm gonna show you
how we do that so
right here you see that i have my name i
have my instagram handle all you gotta
do is go to your transitions and look
for slide this is the transition that i
use
you can drag this right over your image
or your text and then you want to click
on this transition and come up here and
this is where you mess with the settings
so
we have slide in which is exactly what i
want and then at the end it's going to
slide out
and the direction i want to go is right
so that's perfect that's kind of the
preset that it's set to
but you'll see here when it goes to the
other clip
that's not what i want happening so
something wrong is here so i'm going to
click on this transition
and we are going to go back up here we
can see that it's set to slide in i
don't want it to slide in i want it to
slide out
and for the direction i want it to slide
to the left so it goes back that way
now if we watch again
slides in slides out
that's perfect now from here all we have
to do to make the null mult text do the
same
exact thing is hit copy and paste onto
this one
now it's not going to paste both
transitions you need to go back up here
you need to hit command c
click down here hit command v now it has
perfectly
copy and pasted every transition onto
both of them
so when we hit play they both come in at
the same exact time they both go out at
the same exact time if you want to make
these quicker or longer you can drag
this to the left to make it quicker you
can also drag it to the right
to make it last longer be a longer slide
and then you would just match these up
so that they match
and this is just going to come in a bit
slower the next effect i want to show
you guys
is the handheld effect so we're going to
search for a handheld and drag this
over our clip and this is going to give
our static
tripod shot a handheld look so once we
hit play
we're going to see that it looks like
someone is holding the camera
they're a little bit shaky but we can
mess with those settings by clicking
on our video and up here and effects we
can mess with the shakiness and the
distance
if we want to make it more shaky we can
drag it to the right if we want to make
it less shaky we can drag to the left
i like to keep my shakiness around 15 to
10 and then my distance i like to bring
back down about to 10 to 15
as well and we can see what this looks
like now with those settings
it's definitely a lot less shaky this is
a bit more of my taste
and i like to throw this in on videos to
just spice things up and get people on
their toes because when they're seeing
the same shot
over and over again they can start to
tune it out so cropping in cropping out
adding in these handheld effects this is
great for resetting the viewers
attention to get them to watch longer
little stuff like this
does wonders and i think it's a really
cool effect that you can add
to your videos i know i got a lot of
questions on that in a previous video so
for those of you asking
that is exactly how i do it now i've
actually had a lot of people ask me
about this effect that i'm going to show
you guys
as well and this is when the camera
tracks on my face so as i move my face
around
the camera tracks with me let me show
you exactly how i do it and i use
keyframes to do it but there's a trick
here that makes it a whole lot easier so
i'm going to drag
this custom text onto my video and then
i'm just going to add in
the letter x it really could be anything
it could be a dot let's just do a dot
and i'm going to drag this right into
the middle of
my eyes now this looks really weird at
the moment but i promise you guys
it's going to be a really cool effect so
on this clip right now we have
scaled the image so that it is a bit
closer and you can see that as i hit
play
i move my head around like this and i'm
just going to do a little camera track
on my face now the reason i put the dot
right there is because
for these keyframes i want to make sure
that my
middle of my face stays in the center of
the frame the entire time
that is what's going to make this look
really interesting look really cool
and the camera kind of move with my head
as i move it around so now that i have
the video selected i'm going to add
a keyframe and i'm just going to go
frame by frame moving this image around
to stay
on track with this little dot in the
center of the screen
for something like this i'll go forward
every two frames or if there's a lot of
movement i'll just do it frame by frame
but for something like this i could
probably get away by jumping for
two frames adding a keyframe jump
forward two frames again and adding a
new keyframe
and for those of you asking if you're
brand new once you move something around
it automatically adds in a keyframe for
you so all you got to do is start your
keyframes
once and then we can jump forward two
frames once you move it like this you
can see that this has a check mark if i
jump forward two more frames
you can see that it is not selected yet
there is no keyframe but as i move this
around it adds in
a keyframe for me jump for two frames
and just do this throughout the entire
thing
all right now before we watch this we
wanna get rid of this dot so i'll delete
that and then i'm gonna hit the play
button
all right so that's pretty cool so you
can see as you're talking you know it
crops in and it does this funny little
tracking on the face effect again people
ask me about that one that's exactly how
i do it if you want to watch my final
cut pro 10 tutorials for beginners then
click on the screen and check out that
playlist i made it for you guys so
please check it out and i'll see you
guys in the next video
[Music]